Lyza D<mark>anger</mark> Gardner



Hi! I'm Lyza! I am a developer and human, forest dweller of Vermont and steward of the web platform for over 25 years.

I have **over 25 years of experience with the open Web platform**, including stewardship, implementation, writing, consulting, speaking and team leadership. I understand how the Web works and my work is united by open-source web technologies and stellar colleagues. I'm motivated by figuring things out, building things and synthesizing complex information into written or spoken form.

Lyza Danger Gardner

Senior Developer / Web Advocate



Works

Holding functions for event developers. In Charge Curbon Find Transport Curbon Find American Find American

JavaScript on Things: Hacking Hardware for Web Developers

> Head First Mobile Web



I've written two books, chapters in numerous books, columns and articles, and have been interviewed and featured in technical publications. You can view my contributions and activity on GitHub — nearly all of my technical implementation work is public.

What I Can Do

web development and fundamentals

- HTML
- JAVASCRIPT
- CSS
- OPEN WEB STANDARDS
- WEB APIS

Experience

Hypothesis

Lead Engineer and Technical Project Lead

Jan, 2018 - Aug, 2023

At Hypothesis, I participated in the leadership of a world-class team of technologists, building a product that continually pushed the edges of what was possible to do on the web. Described as the team's "glue", I:

- Synthesized and distilled needs out of a complex and sometimesconflicting product landscape into plans for feature design and implementation
- **Applied broad, multi-disciplinary implementation skills**: empathetic coding, technical design, UI/UX, communication, software workflow, and testing to continually deliver exceptional results.
- Brought people together through project management, mentorship
 and consensus-driven teamwork. Drove the creation of team
 engineering values, divining shared values and setting aspirational
 direction. Refined team processes, such as sprint planning and work
 cadence.
- **Got big things** *done*: followed through on big, architectural projects, leading to boosts in performance, reliability and developer velocity.
- Brought design thinking and humanity to my work: designed feature UI; created design systems and built associated library of reusable components; was instrumental in achieving WCAG 2.1 accessibility compliance; reduced CSS payload by 50%.
- Retained commitment to open web standards: aided in design and implementation of APIs conformant to W3C Web Annotation specifications; pushed the edges of web platform APIs.

Bocoup

Open Web Engineer

May, 2016 - Jun, 2017

- ACCESSIBILITY
- PERFORMANCE

exquisite written and spoken communication

- BOOKS
- ARTICLES
- CONFERENCES
- TUTORIALS
- WORKSHOPS
- CODE REVIEWS

empathic, values-based technical leadership

- TEAM LEADERSHIP
- PROJECT MANAGEMENT
- STANDARDS STEWARDSHIP
- PROCESS MANAGEMENT
- OSS CONTRIBUTOR
- MENTORSHIP

full-stack web application development

- NODE.JS
- TYPESCRIPT
- PYTHON
- PHP
- REACT, OR
- JS FRAMEWORK DU JOUR
- TAILWINDCSS, OR
- CSS THINGY DU JOUR
- API DESIGN
- SQL
- ...ETC.

software development methodology

- PROJECT ARCHITECTURE
- DESIGN PATTERNS
- VERSION CONTROL / GIT
- TESTING
- TEAMWORK
- workflows

design thinking and technical humanity

- DESIGN SYSTEMS
- RESPONSIVE DESIGN
- ACCESSIBILITY
- WAI-ARIA
- USER EXPERIENCE (UX)
- USER INTERFACE (UI)
- FEATURE DESIGN

At Bocoup, I continued in my dedication to support and advocate for the open web platform through open-source contribution, open-source-centric consulting projects, and involvement in web technology standards bodies.

During collaboration with Mozilla on a web-testing project, unearthed a decades-old bug across browsers in the anchor element's **target** attribute. Built hardware prototypes on LoRA (wide-area, low-power networking) and other embedded systems using open web technologies.

Cloud Four

Sep, 2007 - Apr, 2016

Co-founder, CTO

Cloud Four is a leading web design and development agency that works with organizations to make the most of the modern web through design systems, responsive web design, and progressive web apps. We pioneered the mobile web. Highlights:

- With co-founder Jason Grigsby, literally wrote the book on the mobile web (*Head First Mobile Web*, O'Reilly)
- Collaborated to build the Obama '08 iPhone app, one of the earliest apps in the App Store
- Helped Walmart design responsively
- Built mobile web apps for clients from Hautelook to local brewery Deschutes
- Organized and hosted the Responsive Field Day event, attracting speakers and attendees from around the world

Intel

Dec, 2004 - Mar, 2006

Internal Communications Specialist and Web Developer

Led visual redesign and optimization of Intranet Web site to coincide with new worldwide corporate branding and logo launch. Championed for new media options (RSS, blogging, etc.) and interactivity at dawn of Web 2.0 era. Covered news beats such as mobility and technology standards, and wrote a widely-read biweekly column ("Lyza Log") which explored new and novel technologies.

Kavi

Aug, 1997 - Sep, 2007

Professional Services Web Developer

Education

University of Birmingham

2000 - 2001

Post-graduate study, Computer Science

Portland State University

1993 - 2000

Bachelor of Arts, Arts and Letters